[SPEAKER_00]: What did we say we're going to talk about?
[SPEAKER_00]: Sensuality and safety.
[SPEAKER_00]: Specifically sensuality, what was... what was the specific thing?
[SPEAKER_03]: Do you have more specific?
[SPEAKER_03]: The domain?
[SPEAKER_01]: The extent?
[SPEAKER_03]: So that people think about it, as in, clarify their thinking on it, once they knew that that's what we're going to talk about.
[SPEAKER_04]: Well, the first thing that you'd want to clarify is when you say the extent of the sensual domain,
[SPEAKER_04]: Do you mean the extent of the range of the physical senses or the extent of like the principle of sensuality?
[SPEAKER_03]: The sensuality.
[SPEAKER_04]: The principle of sensuality.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_04]: What would the sense organs without the principle of sensuality, without having the principle of sensuality in them?
[SPEAKER_04]: It would be just the senses.
[SPEAKER_04]: And that, again, I think, probably would want to be qualified for people as meaning not just... because you have, like, when you say the senses, for example, one would think you have, like, an image of an eye, for example, or an ear.
[SPEAKER_04]: But it really means more, like, the the senses are there where you are seeing, where you are
[SPEAKER_04]: The kind of range of what you can experience through your senses, is what the senses are, in my understanding.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, but can you... would you be able to experience anything through your senses?
[SPEAKER_03]: If the senses were not there in the world as in these flesh organs existing... No, but when...
[SPEAKER_03]: So then the question is, can you... but can you think them?
[SPEAKER_03]: How do you know you have eyes as
[SPEAKER_03]: As something that's necessary for you to see, even if it's like you're looking at your own eyes in the mirror.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_03]: What you see in the mirror is the result of having your eyes.
[SPEAKER_03]: It's not the eyes.
[SPEAKER_04]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, what is then the eye organ in this case?
[SPEAKER_04]: It is, well, the necessary condition for any sight, really, that what in in what whatever there is that is seen,
[SPEAKER_04]: There is... what is, like, in common to all of that, or behind any of that, is what the eye is.
[SPEAKER_04]: But it's...
[SPEAKER_03]: But, practically, from your point of view, where is that eye?
[SPEAKER_03]: Because, obviously, now you're describing it as the necessary condition, and that's all correct, theoretically.
[SPEAKER_03]: But, practically, the eye that sees, while you're describing to me the eye that sees, where is it?
[SPEAKER_03]: What is it?
[SPEAKER_03]: Can you think it?
[SPEAKER_03]: Can you... How can you relate it?
[SPEAKER_03]: So, you will think it.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_03]: It's not can you, can I.
[SPEAKER_03]: You will think it.
[SPEAKER_03]: But will the thought of your eye organ... Can it stand for the eye organ?
[SPEAKER_03]: Or how can it do so?
[SPEAKER_03]: Or can it not do so?
[SPEAKER_03]: So, how can you then know it, if you can't even think it?
[SPEAKER_04]: Well, you can kind of know it by...
[SPEAKER_04]: By realizing that you can't think it, in a way, in the sense that you can... if you are able to distinguish the thought of the I, as in saying, okay, that's a thought that I have, and even that's on the basis of already that there are sights, that there is...
[SPEAKER_04]: That I, I'm, that there's consciousness of sight, as in the things are there, whatever is there, that is seen, it's through, through the eye.
[SPEAKER_04]: But, like, what's funny is that you do
[SPEAKER_04]: You know, if I'm walking in the forest and there's like a branch that is, you know, coming across my path or something, immediately, every... you know, you know that if this branch is going to cut my eye or something, I won't... like, you know that it's a danger to you, you know that it's a problem, you know that you can't see without...
[SPEAKER_03]: So, then, your thought of... about your eyes stands for your eyes.
[SPEAKER_03]: Because why would you then cover your eye organ?
[SPEAKER_03]: As a result of the thought of your eyes might be hurt.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, it does stand for it.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, you can't...
[SPEAKER_03]: It does stand for it in a way, yeah.
[SPEAKER_03]: Okay.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, it stands in a way.
[SPEAKER_03]: You can't...
[SPEAKER_03]: So, what's the problem then, I suppose?
[SPEAKER_02]: That's the question.
[SPEAKER_03]: Where is the... Where is the mistake for somebody who is still not free from sensuality?
[SPEAKER_03]: So, you can't but not have thoughts if you think about your organs, because that's the only way to know them.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, where is the issue then?
[SPEAKER_03]: Because kutujana, asuta kutujana, not free from sensuality, has thoughts about his organs and views about his organs.
[SPEAKER_03]: And now, seemingly, even the one who is free from sensuality would still have thoughts about the organs.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_03]: What's the difference in those thoughts?
[SPEAKER_03]: Where is the difference?
[SPEAKER_03]: Anyone?
[SPEAKER_03]: The assumption... the assuming... How does that manifest as a difference?
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, with sensuality... Are you assuming what?
[SPEAKER_03]: So, the first person has thoughts about the organs, they're not free from sensuality.
[SPEAKER_03]: Another person has the thought about their sense organs, they're free from sensuality.
[SPEAKER_03]: What is the assumption there?
[SPEAKER_00]: That that thought represents an external... yeah, something external to it.
[SPEAKER_03]: Okay, yeah.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, that kind of comes down to...
[SPEAKER_03]: What you put first, that's it.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, both times you have a thought in regard to the sense organs, but the first time you put your thought and your sense of self first.
[SPEAKER_03]: The second instance, the one who is free from sensuality, recognizes the thought as a necessary presence, as a necessary way of a organ to be present, but it does not misconceive the organ to be in the thought.
[SPEAKER_03]: It recognizes that inaccessible physicality, rūpa, present, there, enduring, because of which you are having a thought of it.
[SPEAKER_03]: But it does not conceive that thought to be the first, or to be in rūpa, or rūpa in it, or apart from it, or all these permutations.
[SPEAKER_03]: So you understand, basically, thought for what it is, and it ceases to misrepresent the order of things.
[SPEAKER_03]: That's it.
[SPEAKER_03]: Because if you don't cease to misrepresent the order of things, then things can become mystical, overly mystical.
[SPEAKER_03]: Like, in a sense, all right, so, you know, there are these real senses that I cannot...
[SPEAKER_03]: I can think of, but I cannot access.
[SPEAKER_03]: But, see, saying the real senses creates another sense, or it's just another thought.
[SPEAKER_03]: Another idea of reality, which is again idea, a thought.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, the point is not to discover what's behind your thought, because it's just going to be another thought.
[SPEAKER_03]: The point is to stop putting that thought in a wrong place.
[SPEAKER_03]: Let's say like that.
[SPEAKER_03]: Stop assuming it as first, in regard to what you're trying to think.
[SPEAKER_03]: And that's... that comes down to practically that whole difference between the
[SPEAKER_03]: I'm not sure we should really get into that now, because it might take us in a different direction, but between, like, what's peripherally present while you're thinking, which is another thought, but there is a difference in the nature of thought if it's actually thought and if it's peripherally enduring.
[SPEAKER_03]: If you assume the external point of view, then, yes, you can say, oh, these are all thoughts, but we are not talking about external point of view.
[SPEAKER_03]: We are talking about personal, practical point of view, whereby you are thinking something, which means other things that are not directly thought are peripherally present.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, seeing the difference between the two is where you would undo this wrong order.
[SPEAKER_02]: Would that be the difference between conceiving and thinking?
[SPEAKER_03]: Well, there will be the difference between thinking free from conceiving and thinking not free from conceiving.
[SPEAKER_03]: In other words, thinking results in conceiving, or perpetuates conceiving, and then thinking that it's completely free from conceiving.
[SPEAKER_03]: Either way, exactly, you cannot have thoughts.
[SPEAKER_03]: And people who believe that you cannot have thoughts, and have sort of access to a reality beyond your thoughts, are completely unaware of the blatant contradiction that that all is another thought.
[SPEAKER_03]: Otherwise, how can you even refer to anything outside of your thought, unless you're already thinking it?
[SPEAKER_03]: So, the statement becomes contradiction in terms.
[SPEAKER_04]: I have a friend who's a doctor.
[SPEAKER_04]: And she was saying to me how she finds it strange how, as a doctor, or anybody who studies to become a doctor, like, they study the body very closely.
[SPEAKER_04]: And she said, I know so well all, I know all the types of diseases that the body can have.
[SPEAKER_04]: And, like, I've seen it laid out.
[SPEAKER_04]: I've done, you know,
[SPEAKER_04]: Dissections of dead human bodies.
[SPEAKER_04]: So, how come I don't see the problem with having a body?
[SPEAKER_04]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_04]: So, I find that a good example of what you just said, like the difference between the peripheral thinking in regard to the body, as in seeing it as wherever you go, that this body is there with you.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_03]: Basically, what happens is that people observe.
[SPEAKER_03]: You can observe other bodies.
[SPEAKER_03]: But that becomes basically the extension of your already misconceiving your own senses.
[SPEAKER_03]: Because you forget that you cannot observe your senses in the same sense you can observe the senses of others.
[SPEAKER_03]: Now, I can learn about my eyes by, you know, observing your eyes and your sense organs.
[SPEAKER_03]: But that does not necessarily imply that I need to misconceive mine.
[SPEAKER_03]: And you misconceive your organs when you put the idea, the view about it first, and then kind of assume you're that kind of external position to your own senses.
[SPEAKER_03]: Thus, by looking at your eyes, yes, that's what my eyes are as well.
[SPEAKER_03]: But your eyes can never be seen in that way.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, you can contemplate things externally, as the suttas say, but not losing that peripheral perspective that your eyes can never be seen like that.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, by seeing the external, you know, bodies dying or decomposing, or all those asubha contemplations, for example, you then infer that these enduring sense organs that are peripherally present, the basis for my observation of what I'm looking at, are subjected to the same nature, not the specifics of it.
[SPEAKER_03]: And that's how you get to then undermine that misconceiving and ownership and everything else.
[SPEAKER_03]: And that is the extent of sensuality.
[SPEAKER_03]: The extent of sensuality is the perversion of the order.
[SPEAKER_03]: You unpervert the order, there is no more pursuit of pleasures externally, because it becomes inconceivable.
[SPEAKER_03]: But, in order to be able to unpervert the order, you have to stop maintaining its perversion through actions of body, speech and mind.
[SPEAKER_03]: Like, a person can think all they want.
[SPEAKER_03]: Oh, I'm not misconceiving my senses and I'm contemplating saḷāyātana and so on.
[SPEAKER_03]: But, if body, speech and mind are not withdrawn from sensuality and pursuit of pleasure on account of sense objects, they're perpetuating the perversion of the order and the misconceiving, because the valuing the pleasures of the sense objects is the result of that perversion.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, then, you can do all the contemplations you want.
[SPEAKER_03]: If your actions are still perpetuating the problem, you will not uproot it.
[SPEAKER_03]: But could you uproot the problem of sensuality simply by being restrained, celibate, keeping the precepts?
[SPEAKER_00]: Why not?
[SPEAKER_00]: Because it's...
[SPEAKER_00]: I mean, that's a necessary prerequisite, but it's an assumption.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you have to see...
[SPEAKER_03]: So, say somebody sticks to it.
[SPEAKER_03]: Somebody keeps the precepts, guards the sense doors.
[SPEAKER_03]: What... just on its own, what would that result in?
[SPEAKER_03]: What could that result in?
[SPEAKER_00]: I mean, the strengthening of the mind and
[SPEAKER_00]: It's going in the right direction of understanding.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it's making...
[SPEAKER_02]: So, it would still make a difference.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yeah, for sure.
[SPEAKER_03]: You cannot necessarily... well, you should not expect just on its own to undo all the work.
[SPEAKER_03]: But it is part of the work.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, obviously, just to qualify, if you're keeping the precepts regarding the sense doors correctly,
[SPEAKER_03]: As in, if you take it on as your practice, that reveals your intentions for which you feel responsible and weighed under them.
[SPEAKER_03]: Not if you take virtue, precepts, rules, as a form of, oh, this is a tradition, this is our authority, this community here does that, so I must do that.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's also an assumption.
[SPEAKER_03]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, in that sense, that's just going to probably make you some merit by not engaging with sensuality, but it will not bring you a step closer towards understanding even sensuality, let alone the, you know, atavāda and all the other assumptions.
[SPEAKER_03]: It needs to be taken personally, without the external recourse of, oh, this is the environment that keeps it for me.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, you can obviously use the environment that supports you for the precepts.
[SPEAKER_03]: They will not bombard you with sort of distractions and challenges, but you need to be feeling it on the level of your intentions.
[SPEAKER_03]: And then, even without any instruction, further instruction of dhamma, if you're actually doing it on that level, it is even possible to see the danger in sensuality on your own, simply by abstaining from it, but not in that blind sense, I'm holding these duties religiously because I'm a Buddhist, or because Ajahn said so, or because the community or the tradition or my upbringing.
[SPEAKER_03]: No, no, no.
[SPEAKER_03]: Because I value development of mind through, kind of, discernment
[SPEAKER_03]: And training in regard to my own intentions.
[SPEAKER_03]: Then, if you stick to it, the danger will become apparent.
[SPEAKER_03]: That's why an outsider can become free from sensuality.
[SPEAKER_03]: But, not again...
[SPEAKER_03]: I keep saying that, because people often overlook this, and then they think, okay, so I'll just keep the precepts, and it's like, well, yeah, but how do you keep them?
[SPEAKER_03]: That's a very relevant part.
[SPEAKER_03]: That is the sīlabhātaparamāsa part.
[SPEAKER_03]: That's like the the first three fetches, so...
[SPEAKER_03]: So, they need to be kept rightly.
[SPEAKER_03]: They need to be felt rightly.
[SPEAKER_00]: Feel the weight of the responsibility.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_04]: So, just to clarify, that was something I was going to ask you about, actually, because, yeah, it seems to me that you can, like you said, see the danger in sensuality just by absolutely really keeping to that guarding of
[SPEAKER_04]: Of the senses, seeing the senses as things in themselves, or in... that do not need to be acted upon.
[SPEAKER_04]: So, therefore, you could see the the extent of the freedom that could come from not needing to feed the senses, in a way.
[SPEAKER_04]: But that does not necessarily... What is missing from that, in terms of the Buddha's teaching, it doesn't necessarily free you from Atavada,
[SPEAKER_04]: Because it doesn't imply necessarily understanding of impermanence.
[SPEAKER_04]: Is that... if that is correct?
[SPEAKER_03]: Yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_03]: But a person who has, say, guarded the sense doors, kept the virtue correctly, discerned through their own intentions, abandoned the unwholesome ones, stopped acting out of them, endured them long enough, if they then come across the instruction about anicca, it would be much more self-evident.
[SPEAKER_03]: They will recede much quicker.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, then, atavāda would... abandoning of atavāda will not be as hard as for somebody who hasn't developed their mind at all.
[SPEAKER_04]: And, I think, as you said, and it makes a lot of sense, that it's almost, in theory, that would be possible, but practically, it's not really going to happen.
[SPEAKER_03]: No, because you don't have now, back in the day, you did have, presently, with the Buddha, at the same time, teachers who were teaching the value of abandoning sensuality, the peril, the danger, all of that.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, somebody, without having heard the Buddha's teaching, could have heard teaching about the peril of sensuality, took it on faith, looked for things and then seen it, because it is factually perilous.
[SPEAKER_03]: Today, you won't find teachings outside of the Buddha's, sort of, dhamma, that will be emphasizing peril of sensuality and setting you up correctly.
[SPEAKER_03]: You know, I did see in other sort of practices from India, like Hindu and so on, about, you know, sensuality is very unsatisfactory, with little benefit, but then how you go about it was just like, well, just devote yourself to this deity or that deity, chant this mantra or that mantra.
[SPEAKER_03]: I was like, well, you know, anybody can say that.
[SPEAKER_03]: So that's when, theoretically, yes, somebody can arrive at it, but practically today, given that any detailed instruction of how to abandon even sensuality comes from the dhamma, so it would be impossible for you to not know all the other things that the Buddha was teaching.
[SPEAKER_03]: So then, that brings us to the next point.
[SPEAKER_03]: Jhāna.
[SPEAKER_03]: How do you go about it?
[SPEAKER_03]: Well, let's see, what is jhāna?
[SPEAKER_03]: What would you think a jhāna is?
[SPEAKER_03]: How would you describe it?
[SPEAKER_03]: Because it's obviously relevant to the abandoning of sensuality.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, how?
[SPEAKER_03]: How is it relevant?
[SPEAKER_03]: Do you enter jhāna and then abandon sensuality?
[SPEAKER_03]: Or do you abandon sensuality and then enter jhāna?
[SPEAKER_03]: I don't know.
[SPEAKER_04]: It's a rhetorical question.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_03]: It was.
[SPEAKER_03]: But I still want to hear about jhāna.
[SPEAKER_03]: What is jhāna?
[SPEAKER_01]: It's that safety from sensuality.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yeah?
[SPEAKER_01]: It's a safety from... Seclusion, safety?
[SPEAKER_01]: Seclusion, being withdrawn from sensuality.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, how do you develop that safety?
[SPEAKER_01]: What is a necessary condition for discernment or pursuit or value of safety?
[SPEAKER_02]: See, danger and safety.
[SPEAKER_02]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_03]: You wouldn't be seeking the safety if you don't think you're in danger.
[SPEAKER_04]: I was gonna say... because to even...
[SPEAKER_04]: Somebody can ask about this.
[SPEAKER_04]: How can I achieve this?
[SPEAKER_04]: Or what is that?
[SPEAKER_04]: Or why do you do that?
[SPEAKER_04]: But if that person themselves is not at least
[SPEAKER_04]: It's somewhat dissatisfied already with the pleasures of sensuality, or the kind of pleasure that you can get in general in the life, or taking, at least not taking it for granted that
[SPEAKER_04]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_03]: I think we're kind of presupposing that the person has a degree of dissatisfaction, which is why they would want to practice jhāna, at least correctly in theory.
[SPEAKER_03]: But, despite even, like, people having good intentions, they would go about it in a wrong way.
[SPEAKER_03]: Like, they would expect
[SPEAKER_03]: Certain practices to lead to jhāna, that then in return makes them not want sensuality anymore.
[SPEAKER_03]: And that's the fundamental problem.
[SPEAKER_03]: You will not discern what jhāna is, you will not discern what safety is, for as long as you don't discern the extent of danger.
[SPEAKER_03]: But discerning the extent of danger is what makes you safe.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, you want to enter jhāna, you discern the danger of sensuality.
[SPEAKER_03]: That is jhāna.
[SPEAKER_01]: And the danger of sensuality?
[SPEAKER_03]: We can talk about it now.
[SPEAKER_03]: But, before that, that's why, like in the suttas, that kind of pleasure and seclusion of jhāna, it's always the result of being completely withdrawn and having relinquished, basically, sensual desire.
[SPEAKER_03]: Craving for pleasure, all that.
[SPEAKER_03]: So being withdrawn, secluded from unwholesome states, he feels safe, and then the pleasure of that enduring safety arises.
[SPEAKER_03]: And that's what you can call jhāna.
[SPEAKER_03]: And the point I wanted to add, actually, would be that the danger of sensuality... How would you discern that?
[SPEAKER_03]: Can I tell you?
[SPEAKER_03]: Just do this, do that.
[SPEAKER_03]: Breathe like this, walk like that, sit like this, don't do that.
[SPEAKER_03]: What is the necessary condition for discerning the danger of sensuality?
[SPEAKER_03]: So, the necessary condition for jhāna is to having had developed an enduring sense of safety from unwholesome states of sensuality.
[SPEAKER_03]: Necessary condition for developing that safety is the discernment of the extent of the danger.
[SPEAKER_03]: What is a necessary condition for discerning the extent of the danger?
[SPEAKER_03]: What would you practically do in order to discern the danger?
[SPEAKER_03]: How would you go about it?
[SPEAKER_02]: That's my question.
[SPEAKER_02]: Well, take a look at how you spend your time, 24 hours a day, and how much the value of sensuality determines your actions.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yeah?
[SPEAKER_03]: And say, you have done that, and you have recognized, number of times, that you still go towards sensuality, choose towards sensuality.
[SPEAKER_03]: As we said many times before, sensuality doesn't happen by accident.
[SPEAKER_03]: You always choose it, welcome it, delight in it, act out of it.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, you have recognized some extent.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, what do you do then?
[SPEAKER_03]: How do you deal with that?
[SPEAKER_03]: What can you do once you recognize that, yes, I am engaging with sensuality on some level and still value it?
[SPEAKER_03]: How do you abandon that?
[SPEAKER_00]: Is it discerning the gratification in sensuality?
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, how would you do that?
[SPEAKER_03]: What questions you need to ask?
[SPEAKER_03]: What do you look for?
[SPEAKER_04]: Are we already assuming that somebody is
[SPEAKER_04]: You know, not acting on... Yeah, well, basically, we are talking about us.
[SPEAKER_03]: Let's say that.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_04]: So, what I mean is, like, to what extent, you know, if, let's say, you're in seclusion, or is it, you know, I'm already, throughout my day, I'm seeing...
[SPEAKER_04]: Is it on the level of one is saying, oh, like here, throughout my day, my actions are, to some extent, guided by the acting out of unwholesome, or is it that you are seeing, that you are already choosing to not act out of unwholesome in any way?
[SPEAKER_03]: Well, either way, you can choose to not act, but the mind still values centrality.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, you still haven't seen the danger.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, the question is then, how do you see the danger?
[SPEAKER_03]: Like, that's the only reason you're still valuing centrality.
[SPEAKER_03]: You might not act out of it, you might not be choosing it, but you're still not free from it.
[SPEAKER_03]: Why is that?
[SPEAKER_03]: Because the danger hasn't been fully understood.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, in other words, can you think that you are completely not choosing it anymore, completely not acting out anymore, and still not see the danger?
[SPEAKER_04]: No, you can't.
[SPEAKER_03]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, the point then comes, when you think, yes, I'm restrained, I'm not acting, yet I'm not seeing sensuality.
[SPEAKER_03]: Well, that's impossible.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_03]: If the danger of sensuality is not seen, means on some level you're still welcoming it, delighting it, perpetuating it.
[SPEAKER_04]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_03]: And that's then okay.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, that's what you need to look for and see the connection between the two.
[SPEAKER_01]: Try to see what is dangerous.
[SPEAKER_01]: You have to reflect on why is this dangerous.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_03]: Well, basically, any approach, whether it's through gratification, like, why is this pleasure so valuable to me?
[SPEAKER_03]: What is the gratifying aspect of this delight, of this desire?
[SPEAKER_03]: Or, yes, on some other occasion, what is the dangerous aspect of engaging with it?
[SPEAKER_03]: Either way, the point is to not engage with it and to learn how to not welcome it, so the danger becomes apparent.
[SPEAKER_03]: Because the danger is there.
[SPEAKER_03]: And that's how you get the jhāna.
[SPEAKER_03]: Like, you wouldn't be able to do these reflections and pursue this questioning that would bring the discernment of what you are actually doing on the level of your mind, in terms of welcoming sensuality or not, and so on, unless you have been thoroughly restrained, guarding of the sense doors, and spending your time in seclusion and non-distraction with the external world.
[SPEAKER_03]: But you will certainly not be able to see any of this, if you expect these answers to come magically.
[SPEAKER_03]: Or, even worse, if you expect that end result of jhāna, which is that kind of pleasure of that safety that has been enduring for a while, to come as a result of, like, physical observations of sensations or...
[SPEAKER_03]: So, the questioning of sensuality, discernment of the domain, the extent, the danger, the gratification, is how you get jhāna, is how you withdraw yourself from the unwholesome states.
[SPEAKER_03]: And that's why in the suttas, there are many different ways of inquiry, contemplation, would be the basis for jhāna.
[SPEAKER_03]: In other words, thinking and pondering on account of dead bodies, thinking and pondering on account of, well, ānāpānasati as well, thinking and pondering on account of other aspects of dhamma, usually translated as meditations, but you realize, no, it was just the lines of questioning and discernment done rightly, can then become the basis for safety, i.e.
[SPEAKER_03]: basis for the first jhāna.
[SPEAKER_03]: And I think I saw the ones in the
[SPEAKER_03]: Like a... who was it?
[SPEAKER_02]: Anaponika, I think, did this.
[SPEAKER_03]: It's just a list, compilation, on the basis of, sort of, what's mentioned in the suttas.
[SPEAKER_03]: Like a very commentarial style.
[SPEAKER_03]: And it was like all these contemplations and practices that were mentioned in the suttas, they can serve as a basis for first... they can be... become a first jhāna.
[SPEAKER_00]: But it has to be on the right level.
[SPEAKER_03]: Well, that's what you realize, you know, initially.
[SPEAKER_03]: Also, if I do this jhāna... No, no, no.
[SPEAKER_03]: On account of any of these lines of inquiry and discernment, if you're doing them rightly, because they will result... if you're doing them rightly, they will result in safety from sensuality, because the danger would have become apparent, and that then results in complete sort of seclusion from unwholesome states that you become self-aware of.
[SPEAKER_03]: And that's the jhāna.
[SPEAKER_03]: And that's why, like in the suttas, when the monks were saying, oh, you know, I can obtain jhānas at will and so on.
[SPEAKER_03]: It wasn't because they had this, you know, tapped into some mystical plane that they have always contact with.
[SPEAKER_03]: No, it's because they recognized that by protecting the lifestyle of seclusion, guarding of the sentence doors, virtue, perception of danger, jhāna is perpetually accessible.
[SPEAKER_03]: And it was exactly that.
[SPEAKER_03]: Oh, no, no.
[SPEAKER_03]: That's why I live in these rough forests.
[SPEAKER_03]: Because jhānas are accessible to me at any given time.
[SPEAKER_03]: And that's why jhānas are accessible to me at every given time.
[SPEAKER_03]: Because I live withdrawn in these rough forests.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, jhāna is the result of right withdrawal from unwholesome things, that's sort of followed by discernment.
[SPEAKER_01]: Jhāna is safety from the unwholesome.
[SPEAKER_01]: That was the definition.
[SPEAKER_04]: Sure.
[SPEAKER_04]: Safety from the unwholesome is also the knowledge of the danger.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_03]: As long as, again, knowledge of the danger, got to be the real knowledge of the danger, in a sense, because
[SPEAKER_03]: Inevitably, when somebody practically does begin to contemplate the danger, it will be on the level of theoretical knowledge of the danger, with some kind of...
[SPEAKER_03]: Personal... you can relate it personally to some extent, but the danger really needs to be felt.
[SPEAKER_03]: The danger of... if I welcome this, engage with this, the possibility of that just direction, going in that direction of welcoming centrality or central pleasure, that's already the peril.
[SPEAKER_03]: So...
[SPEAKER_03]: But then, what would be... Oh, you mentioned gratification.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, as I said, another way of discerning what the danger is, is to recognize what gratification is.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, what is the gratifying aspect of sensuality?
[SPEAKER_00]: Delighting in the possibility of getting rid of the pain of one's presently enduring experience.
[SPEAKER_03]: Are you saying, then, that delight is the problem and seeing, hearing, smelling, tasting, touching the sense object of pleasure is not the problem?
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, so... the pleasure isn't in the touch.
[SPEAKER_00]: Stop there.
[SPEAKER_03]: You said yes.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, can you engage with sight, sound, smell, taste, touch of the pleasurable kind without the delight in it?
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_03]: Blanket.
[SPEAKER_03]: Blanket, yes.
[SPEAKER_03]: Always.
[SPEAKER_03]: You can always engage with it.
[SPEAKER_03]: Or other certain smell, taste, touches that always imply delight.
[SPEAKER_00]: Oh, yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Things like sexuality and...
[SPEAKER_00]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_03]: Things that are against the precepts.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_03]: Always imply delight.
[SPEAKER_03]: Always imply perversion of that order.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_03]: But yes, once you say no to those things, then
[SPEAKER_03]: Some engagement with sense objects, whether they're agreeable, disagreeable, or pleasant or not, can sometimes be agreeable, sometimes not.
[SPEAKER_03]: Which means you could remove the delight from those things.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, what is the delight then?
[SPEAKER_03]: What is the delight?
[SPEAKER_00]: It's on the level of the possibility, in the sense that, yeah, you could experience...
[SPEAKER_03]: But practically, practically, if I'm not thinking about possibilities, if those are things a bit too subtle for me,
[SPEAKER_00]: Practically, where is this delight that I obviously have because I obviously pursue sensuality.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, wanting more.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, wanting more pleasure, wanting to get rid of the pain.
[SPEAKER_00]: To get rid of the pain, ultimately.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, then, the the wanting of it... Again, you know, I might not think in terms of getting rid of the pain.
[SPEAKER_03]: You just feel the pressure.
[SPEAKER_03]: The pull.
[SPEAKER_03]: The intensity of sensual desire.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_03]: And then you give in to it.
[SPEAKER_03]: Where is the delight?
[SPEAKER_00]: The possibility of getting rid of that pain.
[SPEAKER_03]: No, but where is my delight?
[SPEAKER_03]: See, possibilities arise as part of things.
[SPEAKER_03]: Delight doesn't.
[SPEAKER_03]: If delight were truly the possibility, you wouldn't be able to free yourself from it.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, yes, there are possibilities of getting rid of it, but I am the one delighting.
[SPEAKER_03]: There is something you are perpetuating.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, how do you not perpetuate your delight in sensuality anymore?
[SPEAKER_01]: I'm not choosing.
[SPEAKER_01]: I'm choosing not to delight.
[SPEAKER_03]: If I'm the one delighting... Can you just choose to not delight?
[SPEAKER_03]: Because you're already, you know, undermined by a delight.
[SPEAKER_03]: You don't start with a neutral position where delight comes and then you choose it not.
[SPEAKER_03]: Maybe, you know, somebody who's been practicing longer can see it coming before it comes, but somebody who's not free from sensuality are always undermined by their delight.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, in other words, you cannot not delight by choice, immediately, certainly, but how do you start uprooting it, so it can become a choice?
[SPEAKER_00]: Yes, so, eh... allowing... yeah, I mean, obviously, virtue and self-restraint, so allowing the... this discomfort to endure...
[SPEAKER_00]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_03]: ...without acting out of it.
[SPEAKER_03]: That will basically... See,
[SPEAKER_03]: Delight is always, exactly as you said before, exemplified through this possibility of dealing with the discomfort.
[SPEAKER_03]: Dealing...
[SPEAKER_03]: So, by welcoming it, welcoming that possibility, you are delighting.
[SPEAKER_03]: And you will do that, inevitably.
[SPEAKER_03]: You can't just say no to that.
[SPEAKER_03]: But what you don't have to do is follow up on that delight.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, you welcome the possibility to get rid of the unpleasant itch and get pleasure as a result of it.
[SPEAKER_03]: Mind is elated at the possibility of it, and you endure that now.
[SPEAKER_03]: And that is much harder, and it becomes, obviously, much more refined, than just saying no to things right, kind of, on the base level, and trying to prevent them from even arising.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_03]: Oh, this mustn't even... No, no, that's the, kind of, whole point.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yes, you say no to base things, such as things that are against the precepts,
[SPEAKER_03]: Things will start arising, delight will start happening.
[SPEAKER_03]: You don't want to get rid of it.
[SPEAKER_03]: You want to be able to endure it without acting out of it.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, in other words, people still delight because they don't see the extent of the delight.
[SPEAKER_03]: That's it.
[SPEAKER_03]: By seeing the extent of the delight and enduring it sufficiently enough, you stop delighting in it.
[SPEAKER_03]: And then, the gratification is understood.
[SPEAKER_03]: Then, the danger is understood.
[SPEAKER_03]: And then, the escape is understood.
[SPEAKER_03]: Escape is not pulling your eyes out or never seeing anything agreeable that was last provoking, like before.
[SPEAKER_03]: The danger is being unable to accept the prospect of delight, to delight in it.
[SPEAKER_03]: Why?
[SPEAKER_03]: Because you understood the danger.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, the danger is of the delight, on the level of mental attitude of delight.
[SPEAKER_03]: That's the peril.
[SPEAKER_03]: That's the biting of the bait that then you're controlled by.
[SPEAKER_03]: Not the actual beautiful things in the world that are agreeable and people lust for.
[SPEAKER_03]: But, yes, in order to get there, first you need to say no to those things, to engage with those things, but then you need to take it on on that internal level, and it's much sharper there, than if our practice is to just sort of adhere and protect and control the circumstances, so that nothing even arises, nothing even crosses my field of vision.
[SPEAKER_03]: It's like, yeah, you don't seek it out, but inevitably things will.
[SPEAKER_03]: Provoke lust and delight in your mind.
[SPEAKER_03]: So what do you do then?
[SPEAKER_03]: You try to negate it, deny it, cover it up, get rid of it, or actually learn how to endure it to its full extent without acting out.
[SPEAKER_03]: And that's why people are afraid to endure it.
[SPEAKER_03]: Because they're doubtful whether they're liked out or not.
[SPEAKER_03]: And you don't want to endure it, because you might act out, and then wait is even more.
[SPEAKER_03]: I might act out, and undermine everything I work for.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yeah, exactly.
[SPEAKER_03]: That's the danger.
[SPEAKER_03]: That's the peril.
[SPEAKER_03]: You endure it long enough, it will become apparent.
[SPEAKER_03]: But if you don't want to let it endure in that sense, and just double down, and redefine the rule, and introduce more rules, that this never ever happens, it's like, you're fighting the problem in a wrong place.
[SPEAKER_00]: You're not seeing that it's arisen by itself, so you're not able to see the extent, because you're trying to put yourself... Well, yeah, you're not able to see the extent, because you're unable to endure its extent.
[SPEAKER_03]: Like, you can see and not see and stuff, but if you're able to endure it without acting out of... it doesn't matter how refined it gets, endure it,
[SPEAKER_03]: It will be seen, the delight.
[SPEAKER_03]: Like, you're already delighting, as I said.
[SPEAKER_03]: It's already welcomed.
[SPEAKER_03]: Okay.
[SPEAKER_03]: I already welcomed this.
[SPEAKER_03]: How do you stop it?
[SPEAKER_03]: No.
[SPEAKER_03]: See, now you're trying to stop it and everything, to get rid of what you already welcomed.
[SPEAKER_03]: You need to endure what you already welcomed, to see the mistake of welcoming it.
[SPEAKER_03]: Not to cover it up.
[SPEAKER_03]: And that's the difference.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you mentioned these contemplations, for example, like a subha, and, yeah, like, one interpretation of a subha is, yeah, like, the the ugly, yeah, you contemplate the ugly, like,
[SPEAKER_00]: As a means of replacing sensuality.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, that's the problem, yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Rather than seeing sensuality is ugly.
[SPEAKER_00]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_03]: And that's where you... You're trying to paste over the view, the idea of ugly, ugly, ugly, ugly, ugly, to kind of push away the unpleasantness of having to endure the delighted sensuality.
[SPEAKER_03]: Instead, the true asubha practice is on the level of if you have endured it already sufficiently enough, you get to see the ugly in it, and then the endurance becomes pleasant.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_03]: Becomes equated with freedom, renunciation.
[SPEAKER_03]: But if you're doing it in response to not wanting to endure it because it's unpleasant, then it's just a cover-up.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_03]: Then it's not done rightly.
[SPEAKER_02]: Then, the wrong order still remains unchanged.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, all of these contemplations, they require this.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_03]: As I say often, that kind of right endurance is the basis for any dhamma approach to apply.
[SPEAKER_00]: Same with, like, ānāpānasati.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_04]: The light in the... different foods of the different senses, to put it like that, as in, like, if the senses are like these six hungry animals, like in that simile.
[SPEAKER_04]: Then...
[SPEAKER_04]: I find it a good image because
[SPEAKER_04]: It really is like that, that these senses are just kind of dragging you and pulling you in the different directions, and the reason that you keep following them, or kind of running after them, that's kind of, in a way, the delight.
[SPEAKER_04]: Like, when you delight in something, that the senses are kind of...
[SPEAKER_04]: dragging you towards, going towards it with them, you don't feel like you're being dragged.
[SPEAKER_04]: So, it's like that's the only feeling of kind of relief or peace, or you're kind of simulating the feeling of relief or peace by kind of following after them, so that you don't see that it's actually them dragging you, not you.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, you don't want to endure the discomfort of being dragged.
[SPEAKER_03]: See, if you stop resisting being dragged around, if you start running with it, the tension will disappear.
[SPEAKER_03]: The dog is yanking you and you try to fight it and then you get all this all this tension and pain and you have to fight it for who knows how long.
[SPEAKER_03]: But if you just start running with it, oh, you don't feel the tension anymore, but you realize, but, yeah, now I have to run, I have to keep moving.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yeah, exactly.
[SPEAKER_03]: All the time.
[SPEAKER_03]: And that's exactly why people would delight, because they don't want to go through discomfort of...
[SPEAKER_03]: Already hungry, wild, untamed senses.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, as I said before, you have an option.
[SPEAKER_03]: You can, yes, keep enabling the wild animal, so it doesn't harass you, or you can endure the harassment, so the animal will calm down, and you can finally train it, and then you don't need to run, nor do you need to fight the attention.
[SPEAKER_04]: But for somebody who's already... that's the thing, that's why you have to start with the... Stop.
[SPEAKER_04]: With stopping.
[SPEAKER_03]: Firstly, yeah, you've got to stand your ground and just hold on to that lesion.
[SPEAKER_04]: Because otherwise you don't even realize that... That's the... that's the simile, wasn't it?
[SPEAKER_03]: The taming of the elephant.
[SPEAKER_03]: Like, you don't bring a wild elephant and immediately start issuing instructions to it, expecting it to obey.
[SPEAKER_03]: No.
[SPEAKER_03]: And then you strap it down to a strong post, tie it down, and it will be kicking, screaming, urinating, defecating, going mental.
[SPEAKER_03]: But...
[SPEAKER_03]: It will have to come down, because it will tire itself out.
[SPEAKER_03]: And if you don't let it run away, if you don't sort of unhook it, it will come down.
[SPEAKER_03]: And then, you know, it will start taking food, and then it will start listening to you.
[SPEAKER_03]: And so you broke it down, broke it in.
[SPEAKER_03]: And that's, that's exactly the training.
[SPEAKER_03]: Like, you can do it, you know, some people can do it more gradually, some...
[SPEAKER_03]: But the point is, yeah, you gotta start containing yourself from spilling outwards,
[SPEAKER_03]: So that then, the mind will learn how to come down within that.
[SPEAKER_03]: Because for as long as there is a possibility for it to go out and relieve itself from, you know, things that are kind of confining, then it will seek it.
[SPEAKER_03]: Only when it renounces, when the senses realize, no, it just, it's not going there.
[SPEAKER_03]: It hasn't been going there for a while.
[SPEAKER_03]: As the Buddha said, the virtue has been developed beforehand.
[SPEAKER_03]: It's a necessary prerequisite.
[SPEAKER_00]: It is counterintuitive at first, because engaging in sensuality does get rid of craving temporarily.
[SPEAKER_03]: Like the dog is screaming and barking and restless and ripping your apartment up.
[SPEAKER_03]: Because it wants food.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, you give it food and it will stop.
[SPEAKER_03]: But see, now, next time we'll do that again, when it wants food.
[SPEAKER_03]: It will cause you damage if you don't give it food.
[SPEAKER_03]: No, actually, yes, I could appease it and get a temporary relief, but as a result of it, I am perpetuating that habit, that it's undermining me further and making things worse and worse.
[SPEAKER_03]: That's exactly your senses.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_04]: That's the five senses.
[SPEAKER_04]: And it's really only by, you know, if you first stop, it's only then that you... You realize how wild the animal is.
[SPEAKER_04]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_03]: Understand that that's the only reason I delight is because the... You will not even recognize the strength of the pull until you stop.
[SPEAKER_03]: Why?
[SPEAKER_03]: Because you've been running with it.
[SPEAKER_03]: But when you stop, then you realize the weight, the intensity of it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Against the grain.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_04]: And that's also, like, the way, I think, to understand the difference between, like, the principle of sensuality, or how I would put it, and, let's say, it's not about just, like, specific types of objects, for example.
[SPEAKER_04]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_04]: It's really the principle of that being pulled.
[SPEAKER_00]: Sure.
[SPEAKER_04]: And I think it's important to maybe emphasize that.
[SPEAKER_03]: In the broadest sense, you start with a specific object, specific acts, as I said, that always imply delight and so on.
[SPEAKER_03]: But, yeah, that's just to contain yourself, so that you realize that delight is what colors the picture, wholesome or unwholesome.
[SPEAKER_03]: So then, I guess, the next point would be danger, to kind of cover the gratification.
[SPEAKER_03]: What is the danger aspect, practically, acutely?
[SPEAKER_03]: What is the danger in delight?
[SPEAKER_03]: So, presence of delight means danger.
[SPEAKER_03]: Why?
[SPEAKER_00]: Nature.
[SPEAKER_00]: We're impermanent.
[SPEAKER_00]: You're inserting yourself.
[SPEAKER_03]: But, you know, things remain impermanent either way.
[SPEAKER_03]: Why is it dangerous for me, that impermanence?
[SPEAKER_00]: Because you're perpetuating this assumption of
[SPEAKER_00]: Being able to control your feelings, which is a false assumption, and so, you're making yourself liable to the impermanence of feelings.
[SPEAKER_03]: How?
[SPEAKER_03]: That's the point.
[SPEAKER_03]: How am I making myself liable?
[SPEAKER_03]: Where is that liability that I'm responsible for, so that this delight is dangerous, making me susceptible to danger?
[SPEAKER_03]: In that assumption... Of?
[SPEAKER_03]: Which one?
[SPEAKER_03]: Of sensuality.
[SPEAKER_03]: But no, the assumption of sensuality is because of the delight.
[SPEAKER_04]: Because when you delight, as in you follow after one of these wild animals, you kind of make yourself part, you become the sense, in a way, you assume the sense.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yes, you take on the ownership whether you want it or not.
[SPEAKER_04]: So, you are taking on that ownership, therefore, it's you who are in some place.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, would you be taking the ownership even if you don't follow that animal?
[SPEAKER_03]: But the delight is there.
[SPEAKER_03]: You're already delighted, but you're not following.
[SPEAKER_03]: You are restrained.
[SPEAKER_03]: Would that be implying the ownership?
[SPEAKER_03]: So, you don't go all the way of following, becoming dependent on pleasure.
[SPEAKER_03]: But the delight is there.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, if the delight is there, is the ownership there?
[SPEAKER_03]: Or it takes time for the ownership to develop?
[SPEAKER_04]: It takes time for the ownership to deliver.
[SPEAKER_04]: No, no.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's not like...
[SPEAKER_02]: This is... you can see in terms of the five holding aggregates, which is what sakāyā is.
[SPEAKER_02]: And, you know, is that holding separate or not?
[SPEAKER_02]: No, it's the delight and lust.
[SPEAKER_02]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_02]: I would say for the six senses, it's basically the same.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, presence of delight is presence of danger, because presence of delight is presence of ownership of that which you cannot own.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, is it then valid for someone who has been following our discussion so far, to start making, at least in their thinking, a clear distinction between, let's say, me here, and six senses, which are wild animals doing their own thing, and I want to keep as separate from that as possible.
[SPEAKER_02]: Not projecting myself into those senses.
[SPEAKER_03]: Ah, no.
[SPEAKER_03]: No, it's not on the level of projection.
[SPEAKER_03]: Basically, first, what person would need to do is recognize that if they think about the senses separate from them, the six animals, or them separate from the senses, that's already the result of the six animals.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, first, they need to find the practical examples of the six animals pulling them, their delighting in the aspect of relief, and then discern them, themselves, on that level.
[SPEAKER_03]: In other words, if you want to contemplate yourself, separate from the animals, you do that on the basis of the animal pull, pressure, pain you have to endure.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yes, so you're going to see yourself in that sense, whether the light, with those senses.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yeah, well, that's what I'm saying.
[SPEAKER_03]: That's where your sense of self is.
[SPEAKER_03]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_03]: Like, you might not see yourself there, if you expect to see yourself elsewhere or in different terms.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, you've got to abandon your expectations of where myself is and start enduring things on the right level and then, again, make the effort
[SPEAKER_03]: To basically prevent yourself from interpreting yourself in these external terms, and actually see that...
[SPEAKER_03]: I might not see it now, I might see it later, but if I understand this correctly, my sense of ownership, i.e.
[SPEAKER_03]: my sense of self, is here on this level of basically pressure of the senses that I don't want to endure, that I'd like to get rid of.
[SPEAKER_03]: That's what it is.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, I don't think you could just extrapolate the contemplation of the self separate from the senses and do it independent of the practical basis of the endurance of the five animals.
[SPEAKER_03]: No.
[SPEAKER_03]: That's kind of the point.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: Because the starting point will be that there's already identification with the senses.
[SPEAKER_02]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_02]: You cannot just decide to step out of the whole domain of senses.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, the closest you can come to discerning
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_03]: So then, practically, the closest you could come to discerning the not-self is to enduring the pull of the animals, without covering it up, without giving in, without justifying it, trying to get rid of it, without managing it, psychologizing it.
[SPEAKER_03]: Because that is that which will truly reveal to you how much you don't own your own senses, your own self.
[SPEAKER_03]: How much, how wild they are, and you, like, you don't even exist for them.
[SPEAKER_03]: A wild dog, you are just a feature in the world.
[SPEAKER_03]: It doesn't care for you, it doesn't respect you, it doesn't listen to you, that's for sure.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, but people do, see, by constantly acting out and running out with these animals, so they don't feel the tension, they develop this, oh, yeah, this is I am, this is mine, uh, my senses obey me, because, look, I can send them here, I can send them there, I can pull them to run to the left.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yeah, but you can't stop, because if you stop, they will rip you apart.
[SPEAKER_03]: Oh, so you're very much just their servant, a convenient servant.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yes, they need you,
[SPEAKER_03]: For directing, like five, five organs, five sense organs need the mind, they meet in it, they get the sense from it, they get the meaning from it, the whole possibilities, but in reality, it's like, which one comes first?
[SPEAKER_03]: Which one is subjugated to the other one?
[SPEAKER_03]: Which one is the servant?
[SPEAKER_03]: Is the mind the servant of the five senses, or has the mind developed so the five senses are basically subordinate to the mind?
[SPEAKER_03]: And yes, for most people, the mind is the servant of the senses, through and through.
[SPEAKER_03]: Although the mind maintains this arrogant assumption that, you know, this is mine, I am in charge, because look, I can turn left, I can turn right.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yeah, but can you stop?
[SPEAKER_01]: But once the senses have calmed down, you've endured the pressure long enough, they've calmed down, then what is revealed is who now is the master.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_03]: The unknown ability, you realize, oh, these
[SPEAKER_03]: I cannot be these animals, because if I were, they would be in my control.
[SPEAKER_03]: But yet, look at them, kicking and screaming.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, I can only tame them.
[SPEAKER_03]: I can only calm them down.
[SPEAKER_03]: But I cannot be them.
[SPEAKER_03]: They cannot be mine.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yes, and so, one can discern the senses already being present, already hunting and chasing things.
[SPEAKER_02]: And secondly, it's not just one sense doing that.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's actually five, simultaneously, in different directions.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah, in their own domains, yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, then, eh...
[SPEAKER_02]: That already undercuts the idea of there being one owner, because it's like walking with five or six different animals on a leash, going in all directions.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, where do you think you're going with all that?
[SPEAKER_03]: And the problem for people is, because if you've been running with them, so you don't experience the pain and the pressure and the pull, you stop seeing them.
[SPEAKER_03]: All you see is yourself running.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, people don't even see the five senses for where they are.
[SPEAKER_03]: And that's exactly that identifying aspect.
[SPEAKER_03]: That gets developed on account of that assumed ownership.
[SPEAKER_03]: Like, you think you are it.
[SPEAKER_03]: You think you are what you see here, smelted.
[SPEAKER_03]: You think you are those senses.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, you put those views, those ideas, first, as we started in the beginning, as we said that.
[SPEAKER_03]: Failing to realize, no, that there are actually physical organs of eyes, nose, the five senses.
[SPEAKER_03]: That I cannot be identified with, even if I want to, because they're endured there in the world, subjected to elements and everything else.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, that contemplation can be enough to make... get you started, so to speak.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, you... you don't identify as much.
[SPEAKER_03]: But, fundamentally, it's gonna boil down whether you're still acting towards it or not, whether you're able to endure the delight for as far as it goes, as sharp as it gets.
[SPEAKER_03]: That... but only if I touch this, the relief will happen.
[SPEAKER_03]: Just... just... just this tiny... no.
[SPEAKER_03]: Because it would be done for the wrong reason out of that perversion.
[SPEAKER_03]: If that's... if the delight is not there, that's fine.
[SPEAKER_03]: Then things are not an issue.
[SPEAKER_03]: If the light is not present, if you have uprooted it.
[SPEAKER_03]: But until that happens, you have to recognize that the danger is not in everything else that would follow on a kind of a gauge.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yes, it is.
[SPEAKER_03]: But the more acute danger of sensuality is on the level of presence of delight.
[SPEAKER_03]: Means ownership is already there.
[SPEAKER_03]: Means wild animals are in charge, at least to that extent.
[SPEAKER_03]: And if you were to recognize truly that even like a second of that perversion of the order implies the danger of the entire domain, you lose everything else possible.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yeah, you realize, oh no, this is...
[SPEAKER_03]: It doesn't matter.
[SPEAKER_03]: Oh, well, it's not as much as before.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yeah, that's good.
[SPEAKER_03]: But just the grain of it is equally bad.
[SPEAKER_03]: A grain of delight.
[SPEAKER_02]: And this is why a non-disciple... a noble disciple can make progress in dhamma by developing the perception of non-delight in the entire world.
[SPEAKER_02]: In the entire world.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yeah, yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_03]: And the Buddha said similar in regard to...
[SPEAKER_03]: Being, isn't it?
[SPEAKER_03]: Like, even the small traces of it.
[SPEAKER_03]: It's like the excrement.
[SPEAKER_03]: Whether it's a, you know, a bucket of it or a tiny... it smells the same.
[SPEAKER_03]: It's horrible.
[SPEAKER_03]: And so, it's a being.
[SPEAKER_03]: Any being.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, whether it's karmabhava or just like being of sensuality or just being cleared from sensuality.
[SPEAKER_03]: Either way, tiny bit of being, it's as bad as a lot of being.
[SPEAKER_03]: It has the same smell, the same danger, the same peril.
[SPEAKER_04]: Like you said, that I find that important, too, not to forget that the senses are these physical things in the world that are just made of matter, subjected to elements.
[SPEAKER_03]: And that's exactly, sorry, like, because we mentioned peripheral in the beginning.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yeah, see, you find very important to not forget that.
[SPEAKER_03]: And you realize, okay, so it's a type of reminding yourself
[SPEAKER_03]: Through certain contexts and contemplations.
[SPEAKER_03]: And that's how you practice that peripheral awareness.
[SPEAKER_03]: See, because you cannot directly perceive those senses.
[SPEAKER_03]: But by reminding of the right order, as in they do have to be in the world they're independent or not identified with.
[SPEAKER_03]: Like, in order I can identify with the senses and forget about them, is because they're already there.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, if you never forget that, that's how you practice the peripheral awareness that we spoke about in our previous videos.
[SPEAKER_03]: Not by some method of, you know, looking peripherally.
[SPEAKER_03]: No.
[SPEAKER_03]: Reminding yourself of the context that's based on the right order and that is why it's helpful.
[SPEAKER_03]: Okay, so just keep that and you can never spill out of it.
[SPEAKER_03]: You know, you can forget, you can get distracted within it.
[SPEAKER_03]: Until you work on that aspect of things, but fundamentally, that will be your kind of outer wall.
[SPEAKER_03]: These senses, I cannot go outside of.
[SPEAKER_03]: I cannot spill outside.
[SPEAKER_03]: I am within them.
[SPEAKER_03]: I am contained in them.
[SPEAKER_03]: They are my ways of accessing the world.
[SPEAKER_04]: Yeah, and so, therefore, that even makes the...
[SPEAKER_04]: The danger of ownership of them, even worse in a way, because not only are you this constant slave of them, but...
[SPEAKER_03]: They're bound for destruction.
[SPEAKER_03]: And you're going that way if you don't abandon them.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_04]: And that becomes your destruction.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yeah, exactly.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_03]: Well, the dogs are running down the cliff.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, unless you learn how to completely detach yourself from the five strands of central pleasures, you will be flying down that cliff as well.